<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Abridgement of the life of Henry the Great, the fourth of that name: King of France and Navarre. Translated out of French</title>
            <title>Sommaire de la vie de Henri IV. English</title>
            <author>Vignolle, fl. 1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02982</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116643</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851859</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851859</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17151</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02982)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17151)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1309:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Abridgement of the life of Henry the Great, the fourth of that name: King of France and Navarre. Translated out of French</title>
                  <title>Sommaire de la vie de Henri IV. English</title>
                  <author>Vignolle, fl. 1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20, [2]   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by M. Flesher] for Nath: Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translator unknown.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  IV, --  King of France, 1553-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17151:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17151:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Abridgement</hi> OF THE LIFE OF HENRY THE GREAT, The fourth of that name: King of FRANCE and NAVARRE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for NATH: BUTTER. 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17151:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17151:2"/>
            <head>To the KING.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Have found an old Manuſcript, which being in mine opinion both judicious and true, I made bold to print and preſent to your Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi>: which if with a quarter of an hours time onely you honor, in very few words you ſhall ſee the glorious life of the King your Father. This life Sir can be imitated by none but your Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi>, and can be offered you by no more faithfull witnes of it then my ſelfe, who not dying under the Fathers commands, have no greater ambition then to end my life in the Sons ſervice, and deſerve by well ſerving to be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by your Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>as <hi>Your moſt humble, moſt obedient, and moſt faithfull ſubject and ſervant, VIGNOLLE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb facs="tcp:17151:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17151:3"/>
            <head>TO THE IMMORTALL MEMORY OF HENRY the Great, the fourth of that name, King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Navarre.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ertue and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune agreed to title this Prince Great, whom the wonders of his life have ſtyl'd Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable. Hee was conceived at <hi>la Fleiche,</hi> borne at <hi>Pau,</hi> paſſed his infancy at <hi>Coyraſe,</hi> in ſharp ayres,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17151:4"/>in the moſt ruſtick exerciſes of the country, that the delicacy of his breeding might not hinder the actions of his courage. At ſeven yeares old hee was brought to Court, to be educated with thoſe to whom by right and merit hee was to ſucceed. The tenderneſſe of his firſt age was hardned by divers great accidents. At nine years old, the King his father dies, the Queene his mother being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, his Vncle in diſgrace, his friends in diſtruſt, and his ſervants in exile. At thirteene he leaves the Court, and to obey his mother, the religion wherein hee was bred. At ſixteene he is made head of a party, whoſe hopes being caſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17151:4"/>downe by the loſſe of foure bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels, relevated themſelves under the favour of his armes, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of his preſence. At nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene he was intangled in a truely funerall wedding, which began with the unexpected death of his mother, and was followed by the loſſe of his liberty, death and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of his. At twenty three he was freed from that captivity, to enter into the ordinary ſervitude of thoſe who command in civill warres. He was often conſtrained to make neceſſity a vertue, and to entertaine his army, even by his army. The dignity of Generall diſpenc'd him not from the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of a common ſouldier, untill
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17151:5"/>he had made his party ſafe by the fift edict of peace. At thirty one the death of the Kings onely bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther raiſed him to the neereſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of the Crowne. The <hi>Flowers de luce</hi> turne towards him and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute him, as the Sunne riſing of <hi>France.</hi> All at once this great calm which they enjoyed, changeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a terrible ſtorme, which pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on him in five yeares ten roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all armies. The battell of <hi>Coutras</hi> the orient of his hopes, manifeſted that he ought to be fear'd by thoſe who lov'd him not. Yet the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of his affaires bereaved him neither of feeling the publique mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, nor of griefe to ſee himſelfe conſtrain'd to vexe his King, to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17151:5"/>whom heretofore he had offered his perſon and friends. The Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy, whereof he was made the argument, <hi>France</hi> the theater, and ſtrangers the authors, was feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully concluded by the death of two Princes, which filled the Kingdome with fire and bloud. The King being ſurprized at <hi>Tours,</hi> was ſo happily relieved by him, that three moneths after he had entred victorious into his capitall City, but for that execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble parricide that ended his life. Then the true French being quite deſolate, apprehending for one King divers Tyrants, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging the juſt cauſe of their lawfull King, caſt themſelves
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17151:6"/>into his armes. He ſeeing the moſt powerfull forces of <hi>Europe</hi> ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt him, the rebels inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and the good ſubjects aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, makes as many combats as treaties, as many ſieges as lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings. He diſgeſts in his Cabinet incredible griefes and perplexities, and overcomes in the field infinite dangers. <hi>Diep</hi> receiving him, ſerves for an example of obedience, <hi>Arques</hi> declares him invincible. <hi>Paris</hi> believing him vanquiſhed, was terrified to ſee him at her gates. <hi>Vendoſme, le Mans, Lizieux, Evreux, Alencon, Verneuil, Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleur</hi> are carryed away by the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of his armes. <hi>Meulan</hi> owes her ſafety to his helpe, <hi>Ivry</hi> ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vates
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17151:6"/>his crowne by a renowned victory, <hi>Mantes</hi> and <hi>Vernon</hi> open their gates to him, <hi>Melun</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives chaſtiſement for her te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merity, S. <hi>Denis</hi> is forced to yeeld, which the enemy taking, is there taken and killed. <hi>Paris</hi> had beene loſt, had hee not fear'd to loſe it. <hi>Corbeil</hi> by her loſſe ruines the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes army, and by him being preſently re-taken, manifeſts his diligence. <hi>Longeval</hi> admires his conduct, <hi>Chartres</hi> his perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, <hi>Noyon</hi> his courage, <hi>Louuiers</hi> his vigilancie, <hi>Aumale</hi> is a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the bloud which hee ſpends for the ſafety of his. <hi>Rouen</hi> reduced to extremity, ſees him meet his enemies to fight with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17151:7"/>them, <hi>Ivetot</hi> diſorders them, <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debecq</hi> covers their flight, <hi>Eſpargnay</hi> advances, and <hi>Dreux</hi> augments the ſhame of it. All the forc'd townes publiſh his power, the rendred his faith, the ſurpriz'd his goodneſſe. Never beaten, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes victorious. His palmes flouriſh in the Provinces, under the reputation of his armes, and the good fortune of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. The ſame day that his preſence gave life to them at <hi>Ivry,</hi> his power produceth them at <hi>Iſſoire,</hi> they ſtretch forth even to <hi>Grenoble,</hi> and further draw <hi>Aix</hi> from out the ſervitude ſhe ſought, and confirme the fidelity of <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux</hi> and <hi>Rennes.</hi> Under their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17151:7"/>ſhadow doe happily ſucceed the battels at <hi>Poncharra, Vignon, Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> and <hi>Villenur.</hi> All <hi>France</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing filled with the glory of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits, confeſſeth, that what he could or hath not done, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne or impoſſible to any other. God who conducted him by the hand to the Throne of his Fathers, fortifies his ſoule by a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular fore-ſight, to break the new deſignes which rendred the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>France</hi> immortall. Hee addes to his victories that of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Stretcheth his armes to the truth, acknowledgeth the Church, the ſacred monument of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors are witneſſe of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of this action, and is ſacred
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17151:8"/>and crowned <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King,</hi> in the moſt ancient Temple of the Chriſtian world. At that change, the pretext which had filled the wicked with audacity, and the good with feare, vaniſht. The Angel guardian of Kings ſaves him from a damnable and enormous attempt on his perſon. <hi>Meaux, Lions, Orleans, Bourges,</hi> acknowledging him, confirme themſelves in their firſt fidelity. He takes <hi>Paris,</hi> makes her ſenſible of the effects of his clemency, ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and felicity enter, juſtice is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſhed, and the authority which ſedition had taken from her, is reſtored. Hee permits the forraigne forces to iſſue, armed to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17151:8"/>the glory of his generoſity, who knowes neither how to feare nor hate his enemies. <hi>Rouen</hi> frees her ſelfe from their yoake, <hi>Laon</hi> is their ſepulture, The townes which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the greateſt in their revolt, imitate them in obedience. <hi>Troyes, Sens, Agen, Charteauthierry, Poicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Peronne, Amyens, Beauvais, Reims,</hi> S. <hi>Malo,</hi> come and offer him the tables of the ſhipwrack they eſcaped. Every where he aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the remembrance of his own injuries, ſweetens the reſentment of the publick, and amongſt ſo many proofes of a royally gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and debonnaire minde, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully cheriſhed by heaven, Hell raiſeth in <hi>Paris</hi> a monſtrous one,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17151:9"/>who hurting him with an execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble knife, leaves on his royall mouth, the mark of the unhappy deſigne it had againſt his life. Hee darts the fire of warre into the Eſtates of thoſe who were pleaſed with the embrazement of <hi>France. Luxemburg, Artois, Piedmont, Savoy,</hi> and <hi>Breſſe,</hi> have tryed what an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended patience can doe, under a great power. <hi>Dijon</hi> renders her ſelfe under his obedience, drawes thither all <hi>Burgundy, Fontaine-Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coiſe,</hi> conſtraines the enemies ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to ſacrifice his pride at the feet of his valor. He enters the <hi>Franche-Conte,</hi> that hath nothing againſt him, but the remaines of his tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyes. <hi>Rome</hi> receives him, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17151:9"/>her anathemaes into bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, acknowledgeth him the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſonne of the Church; his heart being the Temple, and his mouth the oracle of truth, hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth his greateſt enemies to truſt to his word. He happily fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth the civill warres, drownes in the ſea of his clemency all things paſt, Changeth puniſhments into recompences, Pacifies <hi>Provence,</hi> Daunts the obſtinacy of <hi>la Fere, Tholouze</hi> who ſeem'd to have loſt the remembrance of her firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, reſolves to regaine it, <hi>Marſeille</hi> recovers her liberty by the death of the author of her ſervitude. Hee convocates an Aſſembly at <hi>Rouen,</hi> that he might provide by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17151:10"/>of many, for the good of all. <hi>Spaine</hi> knowing by the regaining of <hi>Amiens,</hi> that impoſſibilities yeelded to the juſtice of his armes, askes peace by the mediation of the Common Father of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and to obtaine it, forſakes all the profit of the warre. <hi>Brittanny</hi> followes the good fortune of his victories. He confirmes the edicts, which aſſure the reſt of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to perfect the Peace. He leades his armes into the Alpes, <hi>Montmelliam</hi> trembles to ſee him, <hi>Piedmont</hi> becomes a Frontiere, <hi>Millan</hi> is afraid to be ſo, <hi>Italy</hi> is aſtoniſh't, but hee declares, that hee is armed but to recover his owne, reſiſtance hinders not the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17151:10"/>proſperity of his conqueſts, his pure zeale for the publique reſt, ſtops the courſe of his deſignes. He returnes triumphant, Marryes the moſt Illuſtrious Princeſſe MARY, whom heaven had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Queene of Vertues, before ſhe was ſaluted Queene of <hi>France,</hi> and the bleſſing it beſtowes at this marriage, ſerve to crowne the former, and render the <hi>Flower de luces</hi> eternall. The ſeverity of his juſtice was not yet known, when the inſupportable contempt of his goodneſſe incited and conſtrained him to loſe what hee could not amend, puniſhment to one onely, feare to many, and to all the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. He diſſipates the maligne
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17151:11"/>influences prepared to trouble the State, and ſubverts the intents of thoſe, who having not made warre to get peace, would diſturb the peace to renew the warre. His diligence cur'd the ulcers which careleſneſſe had rendred incurable. He comes, he ſees, he triumphs. <hi>Sedan</hi> unable to ſuffer the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this thunder, ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the temerity of thoſe who will abide the clap. His glorious name gets ſo much authority, that his will is receiv'd for a law, and his counſels for infallible precepts. The Conclave reſpects them, <hi>Italy</hi> honors them, the Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries ſubmit to them; And under the happy auſpices of this peace,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17151:11"/>he enjoyes the reſt which he hath given to all, with the price of his bloud, and of thirty five yeares of his life He keeps united divided ſpirits, tempers paſſions, reſtores ſciences, calls back by edict the exil'd, by decrees repaires the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of warre, ends the great and ſumptuous deſignes of his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſos, beautifies <hi>France</hi> with new ſtructures, both uſefull and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary cauſeth trade and arts to flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, ſo that it ſeemes <hi>France</hi> was caſt downe by the enemies hands, but to elevate it ſelfe higher by his victories. Alwaies <hi>Auguſt,</hi> fear'd and lov'd. From him ſixe royall plints did ſpring forth, which hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ordained for the good and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17151:12"/>glory of his Crowne. [<hi>Three ſons, of which the eldeſt proves himſelfe the true Inheritor of his Fathers greatneſs and vertue: the ſecond his folower to a heavenly inheritance: The third re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains his brothers moſt worthy ſecond. The other three tendreſt and ſueeteſt Lillies, have by their beautifull luſtre raviſhed all eyes, and by their vrtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous odor rejoyced the hearts of all the world: The youngeſt cauſing a cnti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall Spring in</hi> Great Brittany, <hi>The eldeſt a pleaſant qualification of the heat of</hi> Heſperia, <hi>and the Middlemoſt an agreeable aſpect of the rudeſt rocks in</hi> Piedmont.] Hee maniſeſts hs piety, ſhews his magnificence in his buildings, his povidence in his revenues, his liberality in his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17151:12"/>penſions, his judgement in his choice of men, his vivacity in his anſwers, his magnanimity in acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, his faith towards his allyes, his moderation at all times, his prudence in all things, his juſtice towards all men. Invincible in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, Never idle. His royall haire is not growne white but with watching and experience. The Lawrels which crown his head, were gathered in the victorious field of three ſet battels, of thirty five encounters, of one hundred and forty combats, wherein hee fought with his hand, and in three hundred ſieges. And of all theſe is formed the great renowne, which by the ſingular providence of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17151:13"/>God, makes him Protector of the Publick tranquility, Reſtorer of the State, Ornament of the Church, Arbitrator of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of the world.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17151:13"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>AT Ivry, Coutras, Arques</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>immortall fame ſhall ſing</l>
                     <l>The courage, fortune, right,</l>
                     <l>of this moſt valiant King:</l>
                     <l>And ſtouteſt ſtrangers proud,</l>
                     <l>doe quake for very feare,</l>
                     <l>When of the fights of <hi>Coutras,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ivry, Arques</hi> they heare.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
